# 今天赶横溪卖肉（赶集）
Today I went to the farmers market to sell pork.
# 我的肉也没卖完
But I didn't sell all of it.
# 就出去转乡看斗别人有两个甲鱼
I saw a person selling Chinese softshell turtles.
# 我说你的甲鱼怎么卖哦
I asked how much they were.
# 那个卖甲鱼的就说我跟你换
That person said he wanted to trade with me.
# 我拿两个甲鱼给你换2两根猪脚杆
Using his two softshell turtles in exchange for my two pork feet.
# 我说要得要得要得 我换回去整来试一下
I said sure. I wanted to try some softshell turtles.
# 安逸噶
That's good.
# 可以
Yea.
# 现在猪肉好多钱一斤哦
Pork is expensive right now!
# 现在猪肉27-28块钱1斤
Like 27-28 RMB per Jin(0.5kg)
# 27-28块钱1斤
27-28 RMB?
# 两根猪脚换两个甲鱼
Two pork feet for two softshell turtles,
# 划得来噶
that's such a great deal.
# 是啊 两根猪脚我卖了两根卖了168块钱
Yea. Two pork feet would sell for 168 RMB.
# 这两个甲鱼就要值168
Which means those two softshell turtles are worth at least 168 RMB.
# 在市场上168块钱买得到不哦
But you can't buy them for only 168 RMB on the market.
# 差不多这个价
That's about right.
# 差不多啊
Really?
# 这样子我还是没吃亏撒
But it is still a good deal for me.
# 嘿嘿 可能你要亏一点
Hm, you might even lost a little bit.
# 我要亏点啊
For real?
# 要亏点啊
Yep.
# 亏点不多 不关事
It's okay though. Not a big deal.
# 我先烧水嘛 把它烫出来
I am going to boil some water and start cooking.
# 烧来今晚上整来干（吃）了
We will have softshell turtles for dinner.
# 要得 马上整嘛
Nice. Let's do it.
# 要得要得 接都干
Ok. Let's go.
# 这个可能有两斤 你这个换的
This one is probably around 2 Jin (1 kg).
# 我暗（猜）你是亏了丁点儿的
I think you still lost a little bit money for this.
# 亏了不关事 管他的哦
Whatever, I don't really care.
# 反正整来尝哈味道嘛
Let's see how it tastes.
# 这个甲鱼要摸它的尾巴
We have to touch its tail.
# 然后一刀把它的脑壳宰了来把血放了
And then, chop off its head to let it bleed out
# 要放血噶 嗯
For bleeding? Yes
# 这样宰了来放在这 等它慢慢放血
We leave it like this and let it slowly bleed.
# 我看你咋个整
I want to see how you cook it.
# 二天我还是又拿肉换了的话 我就照都这样整来干（吃）
So I can cook it myself if I trade with that person again in the future.
# 那哈儿拿肉换你不得亏本
Come on, you are losing money if you trade with pork feet.
# 这哈儿换有点小亏
A little bit.
# 哎呀 不关事
It is fine.
# 我是不晓得这个单价都嘛
I just didn't know the unit price.
# 晓得这个单价噻我就不可能浪个子哦
I wouldn't be that prodigal otherwise.
# 我还喊他补点钱咯
I would have even asked him to pay me in addition.
# 干脆把它翻过来算了
I will just flip it around.
# 翻过来它脑壳就要伸长
Its head will come out this way.
# 这个是个母的啊
This is a female.
# 翻过来之后它脑壳伸出来它想蹭（翻）过来
Its head will come out when we flip it, because it wants to flip back.
# 趁它蹭过来的时候 耶 你还缩
And when it comes out.... wait it retracts its head again.
# 嘿嘿 它还缩
See, still retracting
# 你翻它过来 翻它过来它又要伸出来
You flip again and it will come out.
# 你倒了霉了
Yikes...
# 好 放着慢慢放血
Okay... Let it slowly bleed.
# 我去挖瓢开水来
I will go get some boiling water.
# 放了血之后拿这个开水跟它淋起下去
After bleeding, pour in the boiling water.
# 这个水也不要开得太凶
The water doesn't have to be super hot.
# 开了就行了嘛 嗯就是微微开那种
Just slightly boiling.
# 把它翻哈
Flip it around.
# 那个皮子很容易就把它烫那种（脱）了
It will be easier to remove the skin if we soak it in boiling water.
# 你就是烫的时候拿手跟它搓
We can rub it with our hands at the same time.
# 跟猪儿皮面上那个薄膜一样
It is like the membranes on pork skins.
# 搓脱一层皮皮过后马上把它弄出来
After a layer of membrane fell off, we take those softshell turtles out.
# 这个不能泡太久
We can't soak them for too long.
# 泡太久就不好整的
Otherwise, it will be bad.
# 这哈子我来教你
Let me teach you.
# 给它搓
Rub it.
# 就跟烫猪脚杆那个皮子样
This is exactly the same as removing membranes from pork legs.
# 啊
Yea.
# 但是没烫都你还不是搓不脱啊
It won't be easy without soaking in the boiling water first.
# 这哈儿就烫都了撒 这皮子一哈就搓下来了
See, it fell off easily if we soak it.
# 哎呀 这农村办席 哪个拿皮子给你整了
Who would spend so much time removing membranes for a meal in the countryside?
# 他还不是就浪个给你整来蒸起蒸起的
People typically just steam it right away.
# 不好吃都嘛浪个子
It will taste bad though.
# 是安 但是老百姓就懂不起撒
Yea, most people don't understand this.
# 很多老百姓都懂不起撒 嗯
Most of them. Yes.
# 这个炒的甲鱼你吃过没有
Have you ever tried fried softshell turtles?
# 没有
No.
# 就是烧的
Only stew?
# 没有 只有蒸的我才吃过 我们办事
Nope. I've only had steamed, in a banquet.
# 就是农村办宴席 生朝满日
Banquet in a countryside will take a full day.
# 打发（嫁）女啊 结婚啊这些整来吃过
We will eat this when someone gets married.
# 这个甲鱼这个边边很好吃
This side of the softshell turtle is delicious.
# 那个裙边是不是哦
The rim?
# 嗯 裙边
Yes.
# 这个团鱼我跟你说嘛四伯爷
Uncle,
# 从中间弄个子开它
we cut it from the middle.
# 弄个子给它割开
Cut it like this.
# 就跟它包都车（转着切）
Cutting while rotating the knife.
# 对 包都车（转着切）
Yes.
# 我们做这个团鱼慢慢地从中间打开
Then, we slowly open it.
# 一定不能着急
Don't rush.
# 慢慢地给它打开了把内脏去除干净
We slowly open it and then remove the entrails.
# 白色的东西就是它的油
The white stuff is the fat.
# 这个肝跟肺还有胆
This is the liver, lung and gallbladder.
# 肝子吃不得嘛吃得哦
Can't we eat the liver?
# 肝子 内脏肠肠之类的就不要噻
Liver, along with the guts, are not good to eat.
# 这个里头都有蛋了
Oh, it has eggs.
# 看 就是弄个子的
See, it's done.
# 你这除了壳壳都没得啥子弄的了
But, it has nothing left besides the shell.
# 是安
Yea...
# 还是猪脚杆安逸点噶 猪脚杆肉多
I kinda prefer pork feet now, they have more meat.
# 老子二回不弄个子跟它换了 干不得
I will never trade my pork feet for this again, no way.
# 我们一般吃甲鱼要先把这个爪子给它去掉
We should remove the claws first.
# 在酒店里面做的话这个一般不会说用那个胆来给它腌一下
In the restaurants, they typically won's use the gallbladders to marinate the softshell turtles.
# 但是自己吃可以搞一下
But we can do it at home.
# 这个甲鱼的苦胆可以放进去腌这个肉 去腥的
The bitterness of the gallbladder can marinate the meat and remove the fishy smell.
# 我拿火锅底料来烧哦 四伯爷
I am using the hotpot base, uncle.
# 要得 反正你说啥子整起好干点就拿啥子整
Sure. Just do whatever you believe will make it tastes good.
# 好 我放了点火锅底料加点这个大蒜辣椒姜
Besides the base, I also have some garlic, chili, and ginger.
# 然后弄点蒜苗一起来烧
Along with some garlic sprouts.
# 要得啊
Okay.
# 一块小点的姜就够了
A small piece of ginger should be enough.
# 要整点泡海椒来呀
Should we use some pickled chili?
# 你泡的都嘛
You made it?
# 在你的罐罐头抓的
I got it from your jar.
# 那里面生花没有
Does it have mildew inside?
# 没有 生花了你放点酒进去就是
No, but we can just pour in some liquor if it does
# 坛沿水还有没得安那里头
Are there water in the opening?
# 坛沿水啊 有
Certainly.
# 就是要注意坛沿水不要它干
Just don't let the water evaporate entirely.
# 一干了就着 干了里头就要坏 嗯
Fungus will start growing if the water evaporates.
# 烧的拍不拍都可以
Because we will be frying, we don't have to slap the garlic sprouts.
# 这个杆杆儿跟叶叶儿分开放
Separate the stems from the leaves.
# 杆杆儿就先下（锅）叶叶儿就后下
We will add in the stems first, then the leaves.
# 差不多了 四伯爷你烧火嘛我来炒
We are ready. Uncle can you heat up the stove and I will start cooking.
# 要得啊
Sure.
# 来嘛
Let's do it.
# 多放点你的菜油哦四伯爷
I will add more of your rapeseed oil.
# 要得
Ok.
# 老子亏本钱哦放多很了
Yo stop! I'm losing so much money!
# 你说来我撤了一哈
Okay I understand.
# 本来想放半斤的都只放了四两
I wanted to use 0.5 Jin (0.25kg) but only had about 2 Liang (0.1kg) in the wok right now.
# 这个不多撒 这里只有可能一两多点油
This is not too much oil, maybe about 1 Liang or something.
# 一两多点 二两嘛
This is 2 Liang! Come on!
# 可能三两油都有
Maybe even 3 Liang!
# 你以为二三两好多点
Do you even know the amount of 2 or 3 Liang?
# 要得了
Okay.
# 好 甲鱼爆香了
Okay, we have brought out the taste of the softshell turtles.
# 诶 你不放点盐在里面啊
Wait, why wouldn't you add salt?
# 放盐 这里面放火锅底料跟这个姜蒜辣椒啊那些
Salt? We have hotpot condiment, along with ginger, garlic, and chili.
# 慢慢给它煸香了多
Slowly fry until aromatic.
# 煸香了再加啤酒下去煮
And then, we add in some beer to boil.
# 伯娘你看 你看嘛
Hi auntie, check this out.
# 肯定好吃撒
Looks so delicious.
# 这是啥子嘛 乌龟是不是哦
What are those? Turtles?
# 团鱼 哦是团鱼
Those are softshell turtles.
# 炒香了哦四伯爷
Uncle, it is fragrant now.
# 嘿 安逸
Nice.
# 放一瓶哦
Add in a bottle of beer.
# 这东西拿来烧魔芋害怕安逸哦噶
It will be better if we can put some konjac in.
# 可以按 魔芋烧起好吃安
Yea, that will also be delicious.
# 魔芋烧鸭子也好吃该是哈 嗯
Konjac is also delicious with duck.
# 就弄个子烧起都很好吃了
But this dish is good enough without konjac.
# 只是说你们平时整不来嘛
It's just that you guys won't be able to make this dish easily.
# 没得哪个整这些来干的
Yea. Nobody eats softshell turtles everyday.
# 这哈子我在屋头没事就整给你们吃
Since I'm here, I will make this for you whenever possible.
# 要得啊
Sure.
# 总整些你们这辈子没吃过的东西给你们吃
Make something you have yet to try.
# 没享受过的嘛你都整点让我享受哈嘛嘿嘿 好
You have been making dish that I had never enjoyed before.
# 其实我们在家里面烧这个团鱼 不用去勾芡
Actually, we don't have to add slurry to thicken the sauce.
# 它这个慢慢收 慢慢收汤汁会收浓的
The sauce will thicken slowly by itself.
# 差不多我放盐巴了四伯爷 要得
Uncle, I am going to add salt now.
# 不要整咸了哈
Don't make it too salty.
# 开玩笑
No way.
# 省都省都得放
Don't add too much.
# 放点盐 然后再放点白糖
Add in some salt, and some sugar.
# 再放点胡椒粉
And then add in some ground pepper.
# 还有最重要的是放点酱油
Last but not least, soy sauce.
# 非常不错这个 特别香
Very good. This smells so fragrant.
# 现在这个汁水有点浓了
The sauce is thickening.
# 四伯爷这哈你看 这汤汁都黏了
Uncle, check this out! The sauce is thickening.
# 慢慢在黏了
Yes, slowly gets thickened.
# 这汤汤儿整来跟它放了豆粉的样噶
It is as if we have used slurry.
# 它这个不是的豆粉 是这个鱼的胶质
But this is not corn starch, this is fish gelatin.
# 鱼胶
Like fish gelatin.
# 一般到了这个时候我们就放辣椒跟这个蒜头
At this moment, we put in the chili and garlic sprouts.
# 然后给它炒匀
And stir-fry.
# 这个蒜苗一断生我们就把它铲起来
This dish is ready to serve as soon as the sprouts get softened.
# 好 端过来点
Okay, give that to me.
# 这个菜我们就炒完了
This dish is finished.
# 这个菜其实最麻烦的就是宰杀这一步
The most complicated step is butchering the softshell turtle.
# 宰杀这一步交给摊主来处理很快的
But it is way easier to leave this step to the vendor.
# 然后我们就剁好 剁好放点调料去烧
All we have to do is preparing some minor ingredients.
# 烧一下 放点辣椒啊放点火锅底料啊姜蒜啊这些特别香
It will turn into a delicious dish with some hotpot condiment, ginger, and garlic.
# 不用烧太久 味道都好得很
We don't have to cook for too long.
# 走 我们端过去吃哈看
Ok, let's go try it.
# 我们这个团鱼它边上那层胶质的东西特别软
The gelatinous thing around the turtle shell is really soft.
# 吃起来还会有一点粘牙 特别好吃
And it sticks to your teeth a little bit, so good!
# 嗯 糍妥糍妥的
Yes, it is teeth-sticky
# 比较适合那种牙口不好的
This dish is especially recommended for those who have weaker teeth.
# 嗯 看都就跟它很绵一样
Yes, it even looks so soft.
# 吃起糍妥糍妥的还安逸
So chewy, yet so delicious.
# 吃这个伯娘
You should try this, auntie.
# 你吃嘛你吃
You should eat as well.
# 嗯可以这东西
This is pretty good.
# 好了本期视频就到这里吧
Okay, I think that's it for this video.
# 我们要继续吃饭
We will keep eating.
# 这个甲鱼说真的特别好吃
This dish is actually so good.
# 我伯爷都给出了很高度的评价
Even my uncle says so.
# 大家可以去试一下
You should try it too.